<?xml version='1.0'?>
    <!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' [
        <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
        <!ENTITY rfc4271 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml'>
        <!ENTITY rfc4760 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4760.xml'>
        <!ENTITY rfc5492 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5492.xml'>
        <!ENTITY rfc8174 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml'>
        <!ENTITY rfc9000 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9000.xml'>
        <!ENTITY I-D.chen-idr-bgp-over-quic PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.draft-chen-idr-bgp-over-quic-00.xml'>
        <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-multisession PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-idr-bgp-multisession-07.xml'>
        ]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="no"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-xxx-idr-bgp-quic-stream-00">
  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="BGP QUIC Streams">Use of Streams in BGP over QUIC</title>

    <author initials="A" surname="Retana"
    fullname="Alvaro Retana">
      <organization>Futurewei Technologies, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2330 Central Expressway</street>
          <city>Santa Clara</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95050</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
       <email>aretana@futurewei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Yingzhen Qu" initials="Y" surname="Qu">
      <organization>Futurewei Technologies, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2330 Central Expressway</street>
          <city>Santa Clara</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95050</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>yingzhen.qu@futurewei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date/>
    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>IDR Workgroup</workgroup>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document specifies the use of QUIC Streams to support multiple BGP
        sessions over one connection in order to achieve high ressiliency.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <!-- ***** MIDDLE MATTER ***** -->

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
	  <t>
	    Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) <xref target="RFC4271"/> uses TCP as its
	    transport protocol.  BGP establishes peer relationship between routers
	    using a TCP session on port 179. TCP provides reliable packet
	    communication.
    </t>
    <t>
      Multiprotocol Extensions for BGP-4 (MP-BGP) <xref target="RFC4760"/>
      allows BGP to carry information for multiple address families and
      sub-families.  However, only a single TCP connection can reach the
      Established state with each peer <xref target="RFC4271"/>.
    </t>
    <t>
      As pointed out by <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-multisession"/>, there
      are some disadvantages of using a single BGP session:
    <list style="empty">
      <t>
        A common criticism of BGP is the fact that most malformed messages
        cause the session to be terminated.  While this behavior is necessary
        for protocol correctness, one may observe that the protocol machinery
        of a given implementation may only be defective with respect to a
        given AFI/SAFI.  Thus, it would be desirable to allow the session
        related to that family to be terminated while leaving other AFI/SAFI
        unaffected.  As BGP is commonly deployed, this is not possible.
      </t>
      <t>
        A second criticism of BGP is that it is difficult or in some cases
        impossible to manage control plane resource contention when BGP is
        used to support diverse services over a single session.  In contrast,
        if a single BGP session carries only information for a single service
        (or related set of services) it may be easier to manage such
        contention.
      </t>
    </list></t>
    <t>
      QUIC <xref target="RFC9000"/> is a new UDP-based multiplexed and secure
      transport protocol. QUIC can provide low latency and encrypted transport
      with resilient connections.  <xref target="I-D.chen-idr-bgp-over-quic"/>
      specifies the procedure to use BGP over QUIC. Complementary to it, this
      document specifies a mechanism to support BGP multisessions using QUIC
      streams.
	  </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements Language">
       <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
        NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
        "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
        when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Multi-Stream Capability">
      <t>-- Only valid for BGP over QUIC; ignore otherwise
         -- Options: control session vs complete independence
         --- Keepalives
         -- Backwards Compatibility (with draft-chen-idr-bgp-over-quic)</t>

      <section title="QUIC Multi-streams">
        <t>QUIC is a UDP-based multiplexed and secure transport protocol.
          It provides connection-oriented and stateful interaction between
          a client and server. QUIC integrates TLS and allow the exchange
          of application data as soon as possible.</t>

        <t>In QUIC, application protocols exchange information via streams,
          and multiple streams can be multiplexed onto an underlying
          connection. Each stream is a separate unidirectional or
          bidirectional channel of "order stream of bytes".
          Each stream has flow control which limits bytes sent on a
          stream.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Multiple BGP sessions over QUIC streams">
        <t>This draft proposes to start BGP peering sessions based on
          AFI/SAFI. It's possible to set but sessions use different options
          , such as proposed in <xref target="I-D.chen-idr-bgp-over-quic"/>,
          but that's out of scope of this draft.
        </t>
        <t>Connection Collision Detection procedure of the BGP specification
          <xref target="RFC4271"/> needs to be modified to allow using
          AFI/SAFI to determine the session uniqueness. Each BGP session
          operates independently.</t>
        <t>Before creating a new session, it should be checked that
          no session exists for the AFI/SAFI peers. If there is an
          existing session for the AFI/SAFI peers, a BGP speaker SHOULD
          NOT attempt to create a new session, and a local error may be
          logged.</t>
        <t>If a BGP speaker receives an OPEN message and there is already
          an existing session for the same AFI/SAFI, it SHOULD ignore
          this OPEN message.</t>
        <t>When a BGP speaker is running multisessions, and there is an
          error, such as malformed message, in one session that requires
          the session to be terminated or reset, it SHOULD only reset
          the session impacted, not any other sessions.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Use of Multiple OPEN Messages">
      <t> Each BGP session is established using its own OPEN message.
        New BGP capability <xref target="RFC5492"/> code to indicate
        that a BGP speaker supports multi sessions is defined.
        <list style="empty">
          <t>Capability code (1 octet): TBD</t>
          <t>Capability length (1 octet): variable</t>
          <t>Capability value (1 octet): flags followed by the AFI/SAFI
             of the session.</t>
        </list></t>
        <figure title="" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
        <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |R|  Reserved   |       AFI                     |     SAFI      |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

        </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>R - indicates this session is a restart.</t>
        <t>Reserved - MUST be set to zero by sender, MUST be ignored
          by receiver.</t>
        <t>AFI/SAFI - //****whether to have AFI/SAFI here or use MP-BGP capability</t>
        <t>When BGP multisession is enabled, BGP speaker MUST advertise
        Multisession capability in OPEN message on every session.</t>
        <t>When BGP over QUIC is used, multisession should be enabled
          by default, unless configured otherwise. BGP speaker MUST
          advertise Multisession Capability in then OPEN message on
          every session. When a multisession capable BGP speaker receives
          an OPEN message without Mutisession Capability, it MUST assume
          the peer is not multisession capable, and fall back to single
          session BGP.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Modifications to FSM">
      <t> TBD.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Operational Considerations">
      <section title="Backford Compatibility">
      <t>For backward compatibility, it is important for multisession
        capable BGP speaker to be able to interoperate with BGP speakers
        which are not multisession capable. There are a few possible
        scenarios listed below:
        <list style="empty">
          <t>ssss</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Session Prioritization">
        <t>One of the major drawbacks of a single session BGP is that
          packets from all AFI/SAFI are sent through this single session,
          and this may cause resource contention.</t>
        <t>QUIC does not provide a mechanism or exchanging prioritization
          information. It relies on the application's receiving priority
          information. QUIC <xref target="RFC9000"/> suggests an
          implementation SHOULD provide ways for an application to indicate
          the relative priority of streams. BGP sessions should be created
          using different priorities. AFI/SAFI that carries routing
          information should be given higher priority.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Other Considerations">
      <t>A configuration command SHOULD be implemented to enable or
        disable multisession.</t>
      <t>Implementations supporting multisession BGP SHOULD have show commands
        to view the state of each individual session, notifications and
        logs.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document does not change the BGP security model.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The document requests IANA to allocate a BGP Capability Code
        as BGP QUIC Multisession Capability. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgement">
      <t>This document references the text and procedures defined in
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-multisession"/>, and we are grateful
        for their contributions.</t>
      <t>
      The authors would like to thank xx for review and comments.
      </t>
    </section>

</middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

<back>
    <references title="Normative References">
        &rfc2119;
        &rfc4271;
        &rfc4760;
        &rfc5492;
        &rfc8174;
        &rfc9000;
        &I-D.chen-idr-bgp-over-quic;
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
        &I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-multisession;

    </references>

</back>
</rfc>
